software engineering radio episode 100
software in space
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
Prince irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our website for supporting the
porkchop
[Music]
welcome listeners to this birthday
episode of se radio this is episode 100
so this episode is about software in
space we talk to hunt URM pop from the
DLR Germany the g-forces and shuffle
often a lot kind of the German NASA
somehow in some way anyway but before we
get started I really want to say a
couple of words about SU radio and how
it has developed as I said this is
episode 100 we have been doing this for
two and a half years now during that
time I think it's fair to say that we've
become one of the premier podcasts and
software engineering thanks to all of
you for listening we have way more than
ten thousand listeners per episode which
is really great the exact numbers are of
course always a little bit fuzzy so well
anyway suffice to say we have modern way
more than ten thousand we were talking
to interesting folks because as your
radio has become well people know it to
some extent people are willing to talk
to us so that's great
that helps make it even more interesting
in the future we also organized or are
probably hopefully organizing the
get-together this autumn we still need
more papers we need more people writing
position papers to come if we look at
the current numbers we bought we don't
have enough people to actually run the
thing so we need more otherwise we have
to cancel it unfortunately a couple of
other things that I want to mention
upcoming changes in SU radio one thing
is that we will have transcripts for all
the episodes we already have two or
three transcripts online I think it's
episodes 88 and 87 if I'm not mistaken
the transcripts are made possible
brought to you by it amos a german
consulting company it a mr. de or a TMS
dot EU if your english-speaking and
michael Manolis helps us get these
things organized
he's a listener who has volunteered to
help with getting the transcripts done
and doing quality assurance and stuff
this is also a call for help to all of
you listeners currently
I do most of the work and it's getting
too much for me I have to step down I
have to do less work for as your radio I
can't continue like that it's it's
really too much work it takes away a lot
from all kinds of other activities among
them earning money if you want to help
with SU radio for example writing show
notes organizing links for topics
putting up the podcasts you know
uploading them and and and editing the
page making sure the people who do the
actual interviews send in their audio
and time all that stuff you know that to
some extent the grunt work off of
keeping the website running of making
sure we have a new podcast every time
there's not that stuff I would really
really really appreciate your help so if
somebody was willing to help us there of
course you'll be part of the SU radio
team please let us know we really
appreciate that as I said I I have to
step down a little bit and do less work
I I really like doing interviews and
stuff and that's true for all of the
others in the team but we need to we
need to get help doing the work part of
it which is keeping the stuff running so
please if you're able to to help please
please contact the team and team at SU
radio donate and help us out I think
that's it let's now get started with the
actual episode with the actual content
as I said it's about software in space
with hands URM pop from DLR this is
another episode recorded at LP and today
we today we are talking to hunt erm pop
from DLR you probably will not know what
that is so welcome and why don't you
tell our listeners a little bit about
you and what DLR is and what they do and
so they know what but it's all about
today about myself I come from the
engineering side I electrical engineer
specializing in control science and very
early I got into I went into the real
time processing business and I from
there I did my PhD in software
ergonomics or who suffer human factors
as it's called in in the US and on the
other hand software engineering methods
specializing in the application
environment of of hospitals and there
again specializing in intensive care
units so where you have high risks where
you can't train people doing their
business with the computers that that
was my special theme in my PhD and from
there moved into the industry into
development of high-risk software or
software for high risk environments and
from there I went into the general IT
environment became the CIO the chief
information officer of one of the
biggest certifiers
in Germany the tuv certain German native
rizzuto as long as it's called and
became a responsible person for the
delivery of the whole IT business of tuv
and now since beginning of 2005 I am the
CIO of the German Aerospace Center in
German it's called
Doge centrum falutin Romford that's why
the abbreviation so we are you can say a
very basic development partner of the
German and the European aircraft and
spacecraft industry that that's our core
business and then we have in travel in
the travel industry in the vehicle
industry and and also in the energy
industry our partners so the topic today
is quality software quality for
mission-critical
space systems and of course some of you
know that
I'm a pilot and an airplane and space
nut so I'm of course very happy to have
the opportunity to talk about that stuff
so we are basing this basically on your
presentation or piece so let's start
with a little history of software in
space you have a couple of nice examples
of how the stuff evolved so why don't
you give our audience somewhat of a
history of all that stuff I I want to
start out from the beginning where
software started to play a major role in
in the construction of spacecrafts that
you can say it began with Mariner 4 and
in 1964 where the first programmed or
kind of software based system was
installed and then from there it began a
cultural change in the minds of the
developer you can say because it took
several years until they really got
aware of the importance of software they
started out looking into Hardware faults
all kinds of redundancy but always
hardware redundancies nobody came to the
conclusion that it could also be a nice
a good idea to have redundant
development teams redundant languages
now so it took a long time and and
several catastrophes to find that out
and in my talk I have some old very old
slides from for us in Germany I would
say the the crash of the Ariane 5 the
the maiden flight of Ariana 5 was the
major point where the German software
developers in in the spacecraft industry
began to introduce quality assurance in
software development that that's the
major point as as most of you might know
the the Ariana 5 crashed just because of
some missing casting so it was just
overflows
that were occurring and that was a
disaster that had cost about 1 billion
euros only some some lines of code could
have rescued that yeah so this was
really a change in the minds and that
there was the beginning of the
foundation of Quality Assurance circles
work groups really dealing with that so
what's the in which language was the
Ariane 5 code written that was a good
language other item but if it's it
doesn't help as long as they love to
write code that's yeah yeah that that
was a de and at that time most of the
code for these really mission critical
software was written in our yeah you
have you have a couple of other examples
of well-known disasters yes how do they
were the same problem basically a coding
flaw or or what what are the typical
reasons for for disasters you have the
a320 crash in mill house so so what are
some of the other reasons why I think I
don't know well what I wanted to point
out is that more and more the disasters
later had and not only programming flaws
as a basis but also severe faults in the
requirements and in hiring in the
analysis of the complete of the whole
system as economics a person I would say
there were a system ergonomic falls that
means you have not only a technical
system but you have a human in the
system and all this together right there
came the faults where the pilot lost or
got lost in the in the in the very
complicated procedures during critical
situations and then they they ate 320
crash is one example where the
manufacturer can obviously say the pilot
is in charge of that disaster but if you
look into the
grams and then they are very complicated
gears working together software side and
hardware side then you can say it's easy
to get lost in there yeah
we're recording this in January not too
long after the be a 38 crash I think it
was the triple 7 and in Heathrow where
people say that both engines were lost
on short final which also doesn't look
like pilot error only so there also
might lurk some some software it sounds
funny and we will see yeah what comes
out we shouldn't be too yeah too early
say something but yeah anyway there is
also something about the mass climate
orbiter I actually wasn't aware that
there was some problem with it so what
was going on there the climate orbiter
was supposed to swing into an orbit
around the mass but there were
calculation errors and the the curve or
the the orbit curve was not calculated
properly so it didn't go into a proper
orbit but crashed on the surface okay
the mass and this was only because the
units the calculation units were mixed
so one team was was calculating in yards
per pound and per second and the others
were in in matrix and this would be no
surprise if the teams would be would
have been in in different countries but
they were both in u.s. the difference so
funny but again it was due to missing
testing environments and missing testing
procedures and what we do today is we
always take out Hardware pieces and
simulate them by software one by one and
so at the end we have the complete
system in software and in hardware so we
have a better chance to find those flaws
so let's go from let's say motivation
through the disasters
to some of solutions let's look at soft
engineering in mission critical systems
what you do there so you have two case
studies here yes those got virtus
whatever the word is is an instrument
that is now as we are speaking orbiting
the Venus and trying to find out
something about the atmosphere of the
Venus and our one of our teams did the
software integration for these infrared
cameras and this was for us a major step
in developing high-risk software and
that's why I have this as a little
example I have also some slides on how
the hardware looks it's it's not very
different from where we know hardware or
is this melamine oh no this is all
certified Hardware because we have
radiation we have high temperatures we
have very low temperature so you have
all kinds you need everything is in pure
gold yes you have better metals gold for
that but it's all certified Hardware of
course and it's not still it's not the
major part of the costs of course to to
have that hardware so how much
processing power is there is it like a
386 486 or how what you know how much
memory do you have any feel for that
well you can in general you can
calculate that I would I would estimate
that we are in the hardware this is
which is used here we you can say maybe
we are 10 years back ok from what we
have now on top ok
so it's very conservative and processors
are always much slower and but also
energy consumption is a big thing so we
are calculating or the the rate is
is much lower to save energy and well
compared to our top computers we have of
course they are slow yeah there's always
this joke there is today more more
computing power on your mobile phone
what they had when they flew to the moon
yes
[Laughter]
anyway what is interesting is is that
these projects are done by teams that
are mixed by by different European from
coming from different European countries
so you not only have the different
languages but of course you have
different cultures and all that so if
you want to have some functioning
software in the end you have to apply
really strict metrics and strict methods
of cooperation so do you use things like
UML or something or to have your own
methods there are there is in this case
we used a UML we use the Rose
environment for that and I come to that
a little later ok
in detail but the hardware in from the
functional point of view is quite what
we know from everyday computer hardware
it's it's better material of course
layers it's conservative it's lower it
has less memory but basically and this
is also a project that has been done in
C so and a part of it is assembler but
most of it is in NC in pure C and any
subset like misra that the people use in
automotive or is it full C with all the
pointer matching and stuff it is it is
just plain C ok but of course the
methods we used and and the testing
environment restricts right the use of
different instructions of certain
instructions or the method is a kind of
a V model the standard V model it has
some more steps in between you usually
don't have but you we are really
focusing on requirements engineering and
in the course of development we had the
most of the problems came from missing
requirements or states we didn't
describe in our state machine based
machine yeah the states in the state
machine were not not described yeah that
was a major error source so can you give
our listeners a little introduction to
the v-model and what you change there I
guess they are more familiar with XP and
other agile processes so they probably
don't know much about the stuffs well
it's the B model of course you most of
most of you will know that you always
have some requirements paper or you have
a design paper and you evaluate that you
you validate that against as certified
results come out of the coding and of
course you can granulate this a little
more usually you just have the paperwork
on on the requirement definition and the
architecture and there we have two more
steps we have after the architectural
design we have a detailed design phase
where we do on a very low level units
testing against a detailed design study
so it's it's more granular but it's it's
basically a V model as you know it okay
well I just wanted to point out that of
course in today's missions we start a
mission before we have reached the end
of the development because it might take
years to to have finalized software and
we start the mission as soon as we have
the basic software in place so a launch
yes launch
so you're saying is ask the spacecraft's
already on its way to whatever wherever
it's going you install we still
calculate that we have to do development
work and we calculate that we we can
earn on the way like on the way if you
if you have a four years mission then at
the end you will of course have several
updates of even core units of the
software in place and in the history
well if you if you go back again to the
Voyager missions then if you wouldn't
have had the choice the chance to update
then this Voyager wouldn't be as active
as it is today and as we speak here
thirty years after launch it's still
this this craft is still speaking to us
recently left the solos
yes yes right in August it left the
solar system and has again given us some
some proofs of special special
astronomic things so it's it's
incredible how long this spacecraft is
on its way and this couldn't be without
severe changes in the coding of course
do you know what the languages were that
have been used back then for Voyager
well that's all assembler okay and I
know that the Voyager as or I as far as
I know it's about four hundred four
thousand instructions you can place
there so and it has a tape recorder to
store data because the memory all
together is only four K and so you need
it for program and for result data and
of course the images Voyager took were
much bigger so they were stores
everything on separate tape recorders
and send them back to earth
flying museum I guess yes fascinating
yeah so before we get to the metrics and
some of the process and review stuff
you're doing just give me some overview
about which languages and operating
systems and other tools you use is it
still as you said mainly see it as a de
still play a role like I can only talk
for for the research side and there we
use mainly C we use as operating systems
of course we have specialized operating
systems for for real-time use that are
that have been used for many years that
are proven of course we had we don't
change to those XYZ you could use links
OS RR or whatever these off-the-shelf
real-time systems are so get down to
this you don't know if your own right
there is there's big experiences most of
the things most of the operating systems
have a long history and they are not
changed very often yeah and before you
mentioned that you use a lot of UML
modeling do you also use cogeneration or
do you code everything manually we don't
use code generation for obvious reasons
because you don't want to maximize risks
we try to reduce the lines of code for
this mission I just mentioned it's only
20,000 lines of code so a very very
small amount but we invested for each
line we invested about half an hour at
least review time yeah or development
here I also somewhere saw the ratio
between application code and test code
and I think it was 12 - yeah 12 to 1 yes
yeah that's also an important thing I
told you that we try to replace hardware
pieces by software hardware in the loop
testing yeah and of course this takes a
lot of coding writer or scaffold around
that so it's it sounds scary but I think
it's it's quite normal that you have if
you have such a high risk code
even if it's a small coach you need a
lot of things around it yeah so okay so
in addition to coding you already
mentioned you do a lot of paperwork
aspects and reviews so can you elaborate
a little bit on the under on the on the
practices you have there well we do
several kinds of automatic code reviews
so so where we try to to automatically
test the code with respect to certain
common flaws or design errors but in the
end we review the code regularly in
teams where we look into the code we try
to explain other developer tries to
explain the code to some person who is
not involved who learns or reviews the
code with the the one the developer
usually is the junior developer and the
senior developer is looking into the
code and asks questions okay which can
be very exhausting for the developer yes
but it helps it helps very much and you
can find much more of the errors if you
do it that way it's it's very expensive
time consuming there but it brings us to
a very high level of our low level of
errors in total I know that from our
work in in the hospital environment also
where this is done regularly and leads
to really very high quality but I guess
it can be a challenge for the ego of the
programmer if their code is basically
said there needs to be a really working
team so they accept criticism from
others thing you you have to do is to
establish a culture of of being free to
do arrows yeah yeah that you you don't
ask why did you do that or stupid idea
but where you where people can feel free
to
[Music]
to talk about problems and of course yes
this this is a you you can't use that in
a hierarchical environment right as you
have it maybe in other industries where
high pressure is in place you need the
freedom to make false and to find them
and to talk about them yeah and many
many catastrophes occurred because this
didn't function because most of the
errors were known were even discussed on
the lower level but the management
closed their eyes and say I don't want
to hear it yeah and yeah for us this is
really a cultural thing prerequisite are
there any other tools you think are
worthwhile mentioning how do you specify
requirements its basic you write a word
document or do you do you do anything
more well we have we have a special tool
for at least for this mission and we try
to establish that that that's requisite
Pro where we do the requirements
engineering there are several other
tools but this our our standard
environment we use for high risk and
developments contains that and for code
verification we use this very good but
also very expensive a tool police pace
and of course configuration management
plays a major role and that we used
click clear case so there's a whole
bunch of tools we try to establish in
DLR for company-wide use yeah I guess
you also to measure quality and and
problems and issues you probably do a
couple of metrics I would guess so can
you say something about the kinds of
metrics you use we of course try to
measure how many faults we program how
many errors we find per day or during
the development and of course the
reasons where do they come from
and where do we have to focus on and
interesting is that we
really we how we divide our development
time the pure development is only 40
percent of the time 25 percent we
invested into management into systems
engineering that's that's the the the
view from really above where you look
into the the techniques and technical
things and the humans are the operators
and and 35 percent we invest into the
design so not touching any keyboard but
just thinking about how to read things
and the integration tests and of course
we try to measure productivity mm-hm
and there we found out that we having
this higher level of quality we can
produce point six lines of code per hour
in the development of course this is a
very small project yeah do you want to
say maybe something so we are actually
nearing the end because you're somewhat
in a hurry you have to do it at the talk
what kind of errors you can find using
the static analysis and coverage tools
what is how do you distinguish between
between what you do in reviews and what
you do with automatic tools well of
course the the the test the coverage
tools can only find a set of of arrows
and most of the arrows still are on the
requirements level or on the on the
semantic level and we we use them we use
the code coverage tools but it's it's
not sufficient still have to review the
whole system and to have a test
environment where you as I say it a way
you test the whole system together the
integration test now where you play the
whole mission through and and see what
happens yes
so it's not it's not enough to to have
the static code analysis yeah okay and
one last thing that I'm interested in is
this redundancy stuff obviously you have
probably redundant hardware sure
and also you try to get rid of those
accidental errors by not using the same
hardware in the two redundant cases you
have different processors I guess you
also do redundancy in software do you do
like one one one software and see the
other one in ADA or assembly language to
make sure the compiler doesn't kill you
there there are parts that are in
different languages but I think even
more important is that you have
different minds involved different teams
one person who is not that deep into
that spec is really looking into the
specification coming from outside
opposing questions that are just yeah
posed with a view from outside the
project and there you find I think the
major flaws of course it would be good
to have software parts written in
different languages that control each
other this is done partially but of
course it's it's a matter of of skills
and in the end costs that you can have
different developers team but in in
medicine of course that is done
regularly I also heard that an air boss
in the flight controls office I do it
yeah heydo and see I think so to wrap
this up why don't you give us your your
summary your lessons learned from the
kinds of projects and and hope that
people who don't necessarily work on
these kinds of things take something
away from that yeah well I have a
mission in my company to establish a
software engineering methodology that is
used by all of our developers that's the
dream and why can I dream of that
because we are spending a hundred
million euros a year for software
development so there is a good reason to
introduce that and of course you always
have the question why should we invest
in that because it costs too much and
it's it's always a problem to convince
people that it's not more money but you
can save money in the end but this is
one of my missions and of course I I try
to remind people that we have in in
these high-risk missions we have to go
forward conservatively in in slow steps
and we have this cultural thing that the
the project manager has to be open for
any remark from the developer where they
say we don't feel good with this and
this or we have we have a problem we see
your problem there it has to be open and
and grab this problem and say let's go
into detail what's what's happening
there because it's gonna come back in
the end and this is one of our our this
this means you have to accept each other
in a team and everybody is free to to
make an error and to report it so once
again it's a people problem yes
[Laughter]
different say one thing yeah so thank
you very much for being on the show I
appreciate it thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the dick reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]